Every year, thousands of Americans die due to pharmaceutical drug mishandling.
Dr. Marv Shepard, the former chairman of the pharmacy administration at the University
of Texas, claims that the typical pharmacy makes two to four mistakes a day, which is
an alarming rate for such a high-stakes action.
By developing and training our own edge-compute model and integrating other machine learning
features, we were confident we could create an automated system to reduce error and increase
public confidence in pharmacists.
With tools like PharmaSuite, we hope to build a new tomorrow where everyone can trust health
care professionals.
PharmaSuite minimizes drug handling errors by monitoring all activities relating to prescription drug handling within a pharmacy.
From the moment an item is shipped to the pharmacy, PharmaSuite keeps track of the quantities, expiration dates, and locations of every drug and pill bottle.
When a pharmacy technician makes a transaction, throws away expired pills, or picks up a new product, PharmaSuite's MongoDB database is automatically updated.
If a pharmacist attempts to place a pill bottle on the wrong shelf, or sell an expired product, they are alerted and the transaction is blocked.
Replay data is collected for each transaction to maximize transparency.
Whenever a pharmacy is low on stock, PharmaSuite will automatically ask providers for new shipment.
Through the full stack, almost all possible sources of error in a pharmacy would be automated.
AI was integrated into our project on every level.
The shipment data was converted into stock information by the meta API ecosystem, which
then used the information to create bounding boxes for where the drugs should be placed
in a way that minimizes the chance of mix-ups.
To prevent the model from invading the privacy of pharmacy technicians,
PharmaSuite only begins tracking the pharmacists when they're making a transaction.
For the next part of our project, we train a custom edge compute model using data from a wearable
inertial measurement unit on the pharmacist's wrist to identify when the pill bottles are picked up or placed.
By collecting 5,000 data points manually, we ensured the neural network could distinguish between idle,
random, putting down, and picking up actions with 98.21% accuracy.
Using YOLO, a computer vision model, we correlate the position of the pharmacist's arm to bounding
boxes to track the movements of pills. After the transaction, it automatically registers changes
in the database, ensuring that the pharmacist returns the pills into the right location.
Through this process, PharmaSuite can make pharmaceutical handling safer and more
trustworthy than ever before for patients while also preserving the privacy of workers.